{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man supervised the removal of the Cherokee from the southeastern U.S. before allowing John Ross to lead the relocation. This man ordered the execution of the Saint Patrick’s Battalion for desertion and treason. Following victories at Veracruz, Cerro Gordo, and Contreras during a successful Mexican-American War campaign, this man ran for president as a Whig in 1852, losing to Franklin Pierce. For ten points, name this American general nicknamed “Old Fuss and Feathers.”",
      "answer": "Winfield Scott A"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. The Carlsbad Decree was enacted specifically to suppress calls for this event. OnewarstartedduringthiseventfeaturedthedecisiveBattleofKoniggratzandresultedintheannexation of Schleswig-Holstein. The Seven Weeks’ War was fought during this event, which France recognized after Paris was captured by Prussia. For ten points, name this event, which was achieved through “blood and iron” and orchestrated by Otto von Bismarck.",
      "answer": [
        "Unification of Germany",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "By brandishing one of these objects, Blanca Canales violated a 1948 Gag Law during the 1950 Jayuya UpRrising. An early version of this object was designed by Ramon Betances for the Lares rebellion. For three weeks in January, 2019, one of these objects was waved by Lin-Manuel Miranda after performances of Hamilton which helped to raise funds after Hurricane Maria. For ten points, name this patriotic object that flies over San Juan in an unincorporated territory of the U.S.",
      "answer": "Flag of Puerto Rico"
    },
    {
      "question": "The definitive history of this conflict is considered to be A Savage War of Peace by Alistair Horne. A national capital’s library was burned to the ground after a massacre in Oran during this conflict. DThis conflict saw several bombings from the OAS, which opposed negotiations with Ahmed Ben Bella. Thousands of pied-noirs fled after this conflict, which ended with the signing of the Evian Accords. For ten points, name this conflict, after which a French colony gained independence.",
      "answer": [
        "Algerian War of Independence",
        "Algerian Revolution",
        "The War of 1 November"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A ruler of this empire who built 102 hospitals was said to have “suffered from the illnesses of his subjects more than from his own.” Water sources in this empire included artificial barays and the Tonle Sap. This empire succeeded the Kingdom of Chenla and was founded by Jayavarman II. This empire built a temple meant to symbolize Mount Meru that served both Hindu and Buddhist traditions. For ten points, name this empire that built Angkor Wat in what is now Cambodia.",
      "answer": [
        "Khmer Empire",
        "Angkor Empire before mentioned,",
        "Kambujadesa T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization was led by the author of Where White Men Fear to Tread, Russell Means, during the seizing of the Mayflower II. Leonard Peltier, a member of this organization, was accused of killing FBI agents Jack Coler and Ronald Williams at Pine Ridge. Members of this organization took over the Bureau of Indian Affairs building in the culmination of the Trail of Broken Treaties. For ten points, name F this Native American interest group that occupied Wounded Knee in 1973.",
      "answer": [
        "American Indian Movement",
        "AIM"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A battle for this city led to the use of damaged Polish swords in coronation ceremonies after Boleslaw the Brave chipped his blade in this city. This city was governed by the “Pravda” or “Justice” code of Yaroslav the Wise, under which it reached its height. The Rurik dynasty ruled a kingdom centered on this city. This city was converted to Christianity by one of its Grand Princes, Vladimir the Great. For ten A points, name this capital of the first East Slavic state, the “land of the Rus.”",
      "answer": "Kiev, Ukraine"
    },
    {
      "question": "Charles Dickens criticized this work as the product of “very feeble amateurs.” Captions in this work are called its namesake tituli, which often feature tildas to indicate abbreviations. Leofwine and Gyrth are shown as fallen knights in this work, whose final remaining caption is the line “And the English left fleeing.” Bishop Odo likely commissioned, for ten points, what work that illustrates how Harold Godwinson lost England to the Norman, William the Conquerer, an 11th century embroidery? R",
      "answer": "Bayeux Tapestry"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man insinuated that the 1999 Moscow apartment bombings were a false flag attack in his book Blowing Up Russia. This man’s wife, Marina, launched an inquest into his death that revealed it was likely planned by the FSB on the orders of Vladimir Putin. After this man, who is reputed to have coined the term “mafia state,” allegedly defected to MI6, he was poisoned after drinking from a polonium-infused teapot. For ten points, name this ex-Russian spy who was assassinated in 2006.",
      "answer": "Alexander Litvinenko D"
    },
    {
      "question": "A man with this surname was created the first Viscount Brome. That man’s youngest son with this surname, Williiam, was an admiral, known for his command of the Channel Fleet during the Napoleonic Wars. William’s oldest brother with this surname oversaw creation of the “Permanent Settlement” that regulated revenues received from India and also served as military governor in Ireland. For ten points, give the surname of Charles, the British general who surrendered at Yorktown.",
      "answer": "Cornwallis T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This kingdom’s “Iron and Golden King” lost this kingdom’s Adriatic coastline and his life in the Battle of Marchfeld. That king, Ottokar II, is buriedFwith many other kings of this region in St. Vitus Cathedral. A man who lost his sight while crusading in Lithuania was the first member of this kingdom’s House of Luxembourg. In this kingdom Jan Zizka led a movement that was named after Jan Hus. For ten points, name this kingdom whose lands were centered in what is today the western portion of the Czech Republic.",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Bohemia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1618, Bohemian Protestant protests against King Ferdinand II led to the second of these violent acts involving windowAs.",
        "answer": "Defenestration of Prague"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man contacted Tom Kahn on the false belief that Kahn added a line to a speech referencing Sherman’s March to the Sea. This man called for “maximum possible” integration while leading a New York City school boycott. This Quaker was the head of the AFl-CIO’s A. Philip Randolph Institute. Strom Thurmond called this man a “communist, draft dodger, and homosexual.” For ten points, name this civil rights activist who was the primary organizer of the 1963 March on Washington. R",
        "answer": "Bayard Rustin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bayard Rustin led the Journey of Reconciliation from DC to North Carolina and back, whose participants are considered to be the first of these people who rode interstate buses into the South to challenge segregation.",
        "answer": "Freedom Riders"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Archaeologist Rodney Young uncovered a tomb popularly associated with this man at the Great D Tumulus. This man was instructed to bathe in the river Pactolus in order to undo a gift he had received. This man received his most famous attribute as a reward from Dionysus after this man cared for Silenus. This man voted in favor of Pan over Apollo for a music contest, causing him to grow the ears of an ass. For ten points, name this legendary king of Phrygia whose touch turned things to gold.",
        "answer": "Midas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A Phrygian legend held that any man who could undo this puzzle, created by Midas and named for the Phrygian capital, would rule Asia. Alexander the Great is said to have solved this puzzle with a sword.",
        "answer": "Gordian knot T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first ruler of this dynasty defeated Georgia at the Battle of Krtsanisi. The overthrow of Lotf Ali Khan brought this dynasty to power after the Zand Dynasty. While in power, a ruler of this dynasty named Mozaffar ad-Din signed his country’s constitution into law. This dynasty came to an end in 1925 when the Majles was forced to depose its ruler by the commander Reza Khan, who become the new Shah. F The Pahlavis took power from, for ten points, what Iranian dynasty?",
        "answer": "Qajar Dynasty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the last Shah of Iran was deposed in 1979, an Islamic republic was declared in Iran with this man as its Supreme Leader",
        "answer": "Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this playwright’s characters, Dikaiopolis, asks the immortal Amphitheus to negotiate a secret peace treaty. Cleisthenes [kly-sthen-eez] becomes an ambassador to a group of women celebrating the Thesmophoria in another play by this author, who depicted a personification of Peace arriving at a meeting between Spartan and Athenian delegates in a work that opens with a meeting of women. For ten points, name this Athenian comic playwright of The Clouds and Lysistrata.",
        "answer": "Aristophanes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While Aristophanes is considered the “Father of Comedy,” his works contained political subtext as Rwell. This work receives its title from its chorus of amphibians, but its text would have brought the exiled general Alcibiades to an Athenian’s mind.",
        "answer": "The Frogs"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man offered himself as a vassal to Alfonso V of Naples in exchange for military support in the Treaty of Gaeta. This man met with the Arianiti and Balsic families in a Venetian-controlled town to form the League of Lezhe. Under the command of this man, Kruje was repeatedly saved from capture by the forces of Mehmed II and Murad II. For ten points, name this Albanian national hero who opposed the D Ottoman Empire in the 15th century.",
        "answer": [
          "Skanderbeg",
          "Gjergj George",
          "Georgius Kastrioti"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "An opera honoring Skanderbeg was composed by this Venetian Roman Catholic priest whose best known work is a group of four violin concerti including “L’autunno” and “La Primavera.”",
        "answer": "Antonio Vivaldi T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Barrell argued that this genre’s “dark side” erased rural social tensions in the works of John Constable and Thomas Gainsborough. In the French academic hierarchy of genres, these works were placed below the prestige of genre scenes but above still lifes. This genre was most influentially developed in France by the Barbizon School, which introduced its plein air method. For ten points, name this genre F of art that focuses on natural scenery.",
        "answer": "Landscapes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Gainsborough’s best known work is likely this piece, modeled on van Dyck’s Charles II and titled not for the mood of the subject, young Jonathan Buttle, but rather the color of his clothing.",
        "answer": "The Blue Boy A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man served as Senator from Ohio after he was elected from a party for whom he coined the slogan “Free men, free labor, free soil.” In his role as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court, this man oversaw the impeachment of Andrew Johnson, years after he had introduced America’s first federal currency in another post. For ten points, name this man whose face is on the ten-thousand dollar bill, who served as Abraham Lincoln’s Secretary of the Treasury.",
        "answer": "Salmon Portland Chase"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When Chase was added to the Supreme Court, he took the seat vacated upon the death of this ChRief Justice who presided over the Dred Scott decision.",
        "answer": "Roger Brooke Taney"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Hudson’s Bay Company...",
      "prompt": "Name the the hudson’s bay company......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Primarily traded this beaver-derived product in its early years F",
          "answer": [
            "Furs",
            "pelts",
            "skins"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Received its charter from this English king who came to power during the Restoration",
          "answer": "Charles II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Primarily operated in this Canadian province, east of Saskatchewan",
          "answer": "Manitoba A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had this future king of England as its second governor",
          "answer": [
            "James II",
            "James Stuart, Duke of York"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was given land named after this noble who was known by the epithet “of the Rhine” during the English Civil War",
          "answer": "Prince Rupert of the Rhine, Duke of Cumberland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was in the same business as these two French explorers, the first Europeans to sail down the MisRsissippi",
          "answer": [
            "Jacques Marquette and Louis Joliet",
            "in either order"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Primarily used this First Nation tribe as a middleman to make their trades",
          "answer": "Cree"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fought the rival North West Company and the Metis at this 1816 battle",
          "answer": "Battle of Seven Oaks D T East Germany"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "East Germany was...",
      "prompt": "Name the east germany was......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Established under the influence of this World War Two Soviet leader F",
          "answer": "Joseph Stalin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Established at this meeting, which finalized the terms of German surrender in World War Two",
          "answer": "Potsdam Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "Patrolled by this secret police",
          "answer": "Stasi A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governed by this political philosophy, in which all party members adhere to party decisions once they have been made",
          "answer": "Democratic centralism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruled by this leader in the 1960s, who nationalized industry in his New Economic System",
          "answer": "Walter Ulbricht"
        },
        {
          "question": "Members of the Prussian nobility whose land was redistributed to farmers R",
          "answer": "Junkers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Starved of this good during a late-70s crisis in which its price quadrupled",
          "answer": "Coffee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last led by this General Secretary, successor to Erich Honecker",
          "answer": "Egon Krenz D T Madagascar"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Madagascar...",
      "prompt": "Name the madagascar......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Contains this native ethnic group which makes up over 90% of the population F",
          "answer": "Malagasy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Contains this city which serves as its capital",
          "answer": "Antananarivo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was suggested as a destination for this ethnoreligious group by Adolf Eichmann",
          "answer": [
            "Jews",
            "Jewish A"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was violently colonized by this French government which crushed the Paris Commune",
          "answer": "Third Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was ruled by three queens of this name in the 19th century",
          "answer": "Ranavalona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lost its queen in 1897 after the French exiled her to this island east of Madagascar",
          "answer": "Reunion R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was led by this two-time president and military leader, nicknamed “Big Man”",
          "answer": "Didier Ratsiraka"
        },
        {
          "question": "In 2018, elected this businessman as president",
          "answer": "Andry Rajoelina D T"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A council in this city codified the filioque clause into Western Christianity and was organized by Bishop Leander. That council alFso directed 23 anathemas against Arianism. Under the Emirate of (20 pts)",
        "Cordoba, a revolt occurred in this city by Abd ar-Rahman, and this city was the location of the “Day of the Ditch” duing which Amrus committed a massacre. This city’s Alcazar was besieged by (10 pts)",
        "Republican forces during the Spanish Civil War. For ten points, name this city, the former capital of the Visigoths and the current capital of Castilla-La Mancha, the capital of Spain under Charles V."
      ],
      "answer": "Toledo, Spain A"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This woman’s parents founded the first free school in Oswego, New York, and she was the only woman in her class at Syracuse. This woman was an early advocate for dress reform, arguing that women’s long skirts were (20 pts)",
        "unhygienic. This woman was captured and arrested as a spy after helping a surgeon perform an amputation. Because the US Army would not issue her a commission, this woman was personally validated by (10 pts)",
        "Andrew Johnson after the war. For ten points, name this woman, the only female surgeon during the Civil War and the only woman ever to earn the Congressional Medal of Honor."
      ],
      "answer": "Dr. Mary Edwards Walker R"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of this composer’s works was composed for the Houston Symphony and memorializes the 150th anniversary of Texas’s declaration of independence from Mexico. This composer created a piece in the aftermath of 9/11 titled (20 pts)",
        "On the Transmigration of Souls. This man composed an opera which features characters including Rambo and the wife of the title character, Marilyn. That opera chronicles the hijacking of the Achille Lauro, while his best known work features the aria “I Am the (10 pts)",
        "Wife of Mao Tse-tung.” For ten points, name this composer of The Death of Klinghoffer and Nixon in China. DANSWER: John Coolidge Adams (4) This event led its country to proclaim September 1 as “Disaster Prevention Day.” To comply with the Washington Naval Treaty, a battleship was being (+) converted into a carrier when it was destroyed during this event. During this event, many people lost their lives in firestorms initially caused by cooking oil. After the destruction of the U.S. Embassy, Cyrus Woods was relocated to the (*) Imperial Hotel, which withstood the force of this event. This event was centered at Izu Oshima and measured 7.9 on the Richter scale. For ten points, name this 1923 natural disaster in Japan."
      ],
      "answer": "1923 Great Kanto earthquake"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two members of this family established the city of Saxonburg in the area surrounding Pittsburgh. One member of this family was the first to manufacture wire rope in America, which he used to create the (20 pts)",
        "Delaware Aqueduct. A structure designed by a member of this family relied on two pneumatic caissons as a foundation. A father and son from this F family oversaw a fourteen year project to create a structure that linked (10 pts)",
        "Manhattan to an eastern borough. For ten points, name this German-American family whose members designed the Brooklyn Bridge."
      ],
      "answer": "Roebling"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) On the first day of this battle, the Congress and Cumberland were destroyed, and a frigate ran aground. On the second day of this battle, Samuel Dana Greene made the A decision to protect the (20 pts)",
        "Minnesota rather than to continue fighting. This battle ended when fragments of paint exploded in the eye of John Worden, temporarily blinding him. This battle took place near Sewell’s Point and proved to be (10 pts)",
        "indecisive as its primary combatants were unable to breach one another’s plating. For ten points, name this clash between the Merrimack and the Monitor, the first combat meeting of ironclads."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Hampton Roads",
        "Battle of Ironclads before mentioned,",
        "Battle of Monitor and Merrimack or Virginia in any order before mentioned 7RThis man was at odds with his younger contemporary, Xunzi, who thought that human nature is to be greedy and self-centered. This thinker explained the idea of the Four Beginnings,",
        "+ “Sprouts,” by using the analogy of a child falling down a well to show the innate goodness of humanity. This man served as an advisor to the King of Qi during the Warring States Period. This thinker was the student of Zisi, the grandson of a man who * founded a school during the Spring and Autumn Period to which this man adhered. Known as the “second sage,” For ten points, name this Confucian philosopher. ANSWER: Mencius",
        "Mengzi D"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to Procopius, the actions of this man only upset Honorius because he thought his favorite chicken had died. This man died while besieging Consenza but had legendarily pre-planned to have the River (20 pts)",
        "Busento rerouted to cover his grave. This man’s soldiers burned the Gardens of Sallust and ransacked the Mausoleum of Augustus. This non-Roman fought under (10 pts)",
        "Theodosius I at the Battle of the Frigidus and led several campaigns against Stilicho. For ten points, name this “ruler of all,” the first king of the Visigoths who sacked Rome in 410."
      ],
      "answer": "Alaric I T"
    }
  ]
}